<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The last articles of peace made, concluded, accorded and agreed upon the 30 day of Iuly, 1646, by and between His Excellency, James Lord Marques of Ormond, Lord Lieutenant General, and General Governor of His Majesties Kingdom of Ireland, His Majesties Commisssioner, to treat and conclude a peace with His Majesties Roman Catholique subjects of the said kingdom, by vertue of His Majesties Commission under the great seal of England bearing date at Buckingham on the 24 day of June, in the twentieth year of his reign, for and on the behalf of His Most Excellent Majesty of the one part, and Donogh Lord Viscount Muskery and others appointed and authorized by His Majesties said Roman Catholique subjects, by vertue of an authority of the said Roman Catholique subjects, bearing date the sixth day of March, 1645, and in the one and twentieth year of His Majesties reign, of the other part.</title>
            <author>Ireland. Lord Lieutenant (1641-1649 : Ormonde)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53435</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O446</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6410</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12988408</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12988408</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96244</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53435)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96244)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 724:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The last articles of peace made, concluded, accorded and agreed upon the 30 day of Iuly, 1646, by and between His Excellency, James Lord Marques of Ormond, Lord Lieutenant General, and General Governor of His Majesties Kingdom of Ireland, His Majesties Commisssioner, to treat and conclude a peace with His Majesties Roman Catholique subjects of the said kingdom, by vertue of His Majesties Commission under the great seal of England bearing date at Buckingham on the 24 day of June, in the twentieth year of his reign, for and on the behalf of His Most Excellent Majesty of the one part, and Donogh Lord Viscount Muskery and others appointed and authorized by His Majesties said Roman Catholique subjects, by vertue of an authority of the said Roman Catholique subjects, bearing date the sixth day of March, 1645, and in the one and twentieth year of His Majesties reign, of the other part.</title>
                  <author>Ireland. Lord Lieutenant (1641-1649 : Ormonde)</author>
                  <author>Ormonde, James Butler, Duke of, 1610-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by W. Bladen ... ;</publisher>
                  <publisher>for Edw. Husband ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted first at Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <pubPlace>and now reprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Sept. 7, 1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1625-1649 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96244:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96244:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The laſt ARTICLES OF PEACE Made, Concluded, Accorded and Agreed upon the 30. day of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1646. by and between His Excellency, <hi>James</hi> Lord Marques of <hi>Ormond,</hi> Lord Lieutenant General, and General Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of His Majeſties Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> His Majeſties Commiſſioner, to Treat and Conclude a Peace with His Majeſties Roman Catholique Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the ſaid Kingdom, by vertue of His Majeſties Commiſſion under the Great Seal of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bearing date at <hi>Buckingham</hi> on the 24. day of <hi>June,</hi> in the Twentieth year of His Reign, for and on the behalf of His moſt Excellent Majeſty of the one part;</p>
            <p>AND <hi>Donogh</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Muskery,</hi> and others appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Authorized by His Majeſties ſaid Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Subjects, by vertue of an Authority of the ſaid Roman Catholique Subjects, bearing date the ſixth day of <hi>March,</hi> 1645. and in the One and twentieth year of His Majeſties Reign, of the other part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bliſhed by Authority and Command of the Lord Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Councel there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted firſt at <hi>Dublin</hi> by <hi>William Bladen,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty; and now Reprinted at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>Edw. Husband,</hi> Printer to the Honorable Houſe of Commons, <hi>Sept.</hi> 7.1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:96244:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96244:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the Lord Lieutenant and COUNCEL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>ORMOND.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>VHereas Articles of Peace are made, concluded, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and agreed upon, by and between Us, <hi>James</hi> Lord Marques of <hi>Ormond,</hi> Lord Lieutenant General, and General Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of His Majeſties Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> His Majeſties Commiſsioner to Treat and conclude a Peace with His Majeſties Roman Catholique Subjects of the ſaid Kingdom, by vertue of His Majeſties Commiſsion under the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> bearing Date at <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kingham</hi> on the <hi>24.</hi> day of <hi>June,</hi> in the Twentieth year of His Raign, for and on the behalf of His moſt Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of the one part; and <hi>Donogh</hi> Lord
<pb facs="tcp:96244:3"/>Viſcount <hi>Muskery</hi> and others, appointed and Authorized by His Majeſties ſaid Roman Catholique Subjects, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of an Authority of the ſaid Roman Catholique Subjects, bearing Date the ſixth day of <hi>March, 1645.</hi> and in the <hi>21.</hi> year of His Majeſties Raign, of the other part, a true Copy of which Articles of Peace is hereunto annexed, Wee the Lord Lieutenant and Councel do by this Proclamation in His Majeſties Name publiſh the ſame, And do, in His Majeſties Name, ſtrictly charge and command all His Majeſties Subjects, and all others Inhabiting or Reſiding within His Majeſties ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to take notice thereof, and to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der due Obedience to the ſame in all the parts thereof.</p>
            <p>And as His Majeſty hath been indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to this Peace out of a deep ſence of the miſeries and calamities brought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this His Kingdom and people, and out of a hope conceived by His Majeſty that it may prevent the further effuſion of His Subjects blood, redeem them out
<pb facs="tcp:96244:3"/>of all the miſeries and calamities under which they now ſuffer, reſtore them to all quietneſs and happineſs under His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties moſt gracious Government, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Kingdom in general from thoſe ſlaughters, deprecations, rapines &amp; ſpoils which always accompany a War, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the Subjects and others with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to betake themſelvs to Trade, Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique, Commerce, Manufacture, and all other things which uninterrupted may increaſe the wealth and ſtrength of the Kingdom, beget in all His Majeſties Sujects of this Kingdom, a perfect Unity amongſt themſelves, after the too long continued Diviſion amongſt them: So His Majeſty aſſures Himſelf that all His Subjects of this His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom (duly conſidering the great and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable benefits which they may finde in this Peace) will with all duty render due obedience thereunto. And We, in His Majeſties Name do hereby Declare, That all perſons ſo rendring due Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the ſaid Peace, ſhall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, cheriſhed, countenanced and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
<pb facs="tcp:96244:4"/>by His Majeſty and His Royal Authority, according to the true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and meaning of the ſaid Articles of Peace.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at His Majeſties Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> 
                  <date>the Thirtieth day of July, 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Ri. Bolton, Canc.</item>
                     <item>Roſcomon.</item>
                     <item>Cha. Lambart.</item>
                     <item>Gerrard Lowther.</item>
                     <item>Fr. Willoughby.</item>
                     <item>Robert Forth.</item>
                     <item>Dillon.</item>
                     <item>La. Dublin.</item>
                     <item>Geo. Cloyne.</item>
                     <item>Arthur Chicheſter.</item>
                     <item>Hen. Tichborn.</item>
                     <item>Tho. Lucas.</item>
                     <item>Ja. Ware.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <closer>God ſave the King.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="articles_of_peace">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96244:4"/>
            <head>Articles of Peace made, concluded, accorded, and agreed upon, by and between his Excellency <hi>IAMES</hi> Lord Marques of Ormond, Lord Lieutenant General, and General Governour of His Majeſties Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> His Majeſties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner to Treat and conclude a Peace with His Majeſties Roman Catholique Subjects of the ſaid Kingdom, by vertue of His Majeſties Commiſſion under the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> bearing date at <hi>Buckingham,</hi> the <hi>24.</hi> day of <hi>Iune,</hi> in the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth year of His Raign, for and on the behalf of His moſt Excellent Majeſty, of the one party; And <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Mountgarret, Donogh</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Muskery,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Talbot</hi> Baronet, <hi>Dermot O Bryen, Patrick Darcy, Gefferey Brown,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Dillon,</hi> Eſquires, Appointed and Authorized by His Majeſties ſaid Roman Catholique Subjects by vertue of an Authority of the ſaid Roman Catholique Subjects, bearing date the ſixth day of March, <hi>Anno Domini,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred forty five, and in the twenty one year of His Majeſties Raign, Authorizing them and others, or any four or more of them to Treat and Conclude a Peace in the ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with His Majeſties ſaid Commiſſioner, for and in the behalf of His Majeſties ſaid Roman Catholique Subjects on the other party.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Nprimis,</hi> It is Concluded, Accorded and Agreed upon, by His Majeſties ſaid Commiſſioner, for and on the behalf of His moſt Excellent Majeſty, and the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Mountgarret, Donogh</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Muskery,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot</hi> Baronet, <hi>Dermot O Bryen, Patrick, Darcy, Geffery Brown</hi> and <hi>John Dillon,</hi> Eſquires, on the behalf of the ſaid Roman Catholique Subjects; And His Majeſty is graciouſly pleaſed, that it ſhall be provided by Act of Parliament to be paſſed in the next Parliament to be held in this Kingdom, That
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96244:5"/>the Profeſſors of the Roman Catholique Religion in the ſaid King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or any of them be not bound or obliged to take this Oath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Statute of <hi>Secundo Eliz:</hi> commonly called <hi>the Oath of Supremacy,</hi> And that the ſaid Oath ſhall not be tendred unto them, and that the refuſal of the ſaid Oath ſhall not redound to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of them, or any of them, they taking the Oath of Allegiance <hi>In haec verba. I.</hi> A. B. <hi>do truely acknowledge, confeſſe, teſtifie, and declare in my conſcience before God and the World, That our Soveraign Lord King</hi> CHARLES <hi>is Lawful and Rightful King of this Realm, and of other His Majeſties Dominions and Countryes, and I will bear Faith and true Allegience to His Majeſty, and His Heires and Succeſſors, and Him and them will defend to the uttermoſt of my power againſt all conſpiracies and attempts whatſover, which ſhall be made againſt His or their Crown or Dignity, and do my beſt endeavor to diſcloſe and make known unto His Majeſty, His Heires and Succeſſors, or to the Lord Deputy or other Governor for the time being, all Treaſons or Trayterous Conspiracies, which I ſhall know or hear to be intended againſt His Majeſty or any of them, and I do make this recognition and acknowledgement heartily, willingly, and truely, upon the true faith of a Chriſtian. So help me God, &amp;c.</hi> So as by the ſame Act it be further Provided and Enacted, that if any Roman Catholique happen to be promoted, preſented or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to any Eccleſiaſtical promotion, dignity or benifice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the form now uſed in the Proteſtant Church of <hi>Ireland,</hi> That the freedom and exemption aforeſaid ſhall not extend to any ſuch Roman Catholique; Or if any being Proteſtant, be advanced, promoted or preſented to any Eccleſiaſtical benefice, dignity or promotion, ſhall afterwards happen to become a Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, that the freedom and exemption aforeſaid ſhall not ſo far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to any ſuch Roman Catholique, but that upon tender of the ſaid Oath, and refuſal thereof, he be for that cauſe left ſubject to privation of the ſaid benefice, dignity or promotion, according to the ſaid Statute; And it is further concluded, accorded and agreed, by and between the ſaid parties, that for all matters concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt Propoſition of the ſaid Catholiques, <hi>viz.</hi> That all Acts made againſt the profeſſors of the Roman Catholique Faith, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by any reſtraint, penalty, mulct, or incapacity, may be laid upon
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96244:5"/>any Roman Catholique within the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> may be Repealed, and the ſaid Catholiques to be allowed the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Roman Catholique Religion. That His Majeſties ſaid Roman Catholique Subjects be referred to His Majeſties gracious Favor and further Conceſſions; And that no clauſe in theſe A'rticles ſhall or may hinder His Majeſties ſaid Roman Catholique Subjects, or any of them from the benefit of His Majeſties further Graces and Conceſſions; And that no uſe ſhall be made of the Papers paſt on this Treaty, or any of them, concerning the ſaid firſt Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, which may in any ſort hinder the ſaid Roman Catholique Subjects, or any of them, from His Majeſties further Conceſſions. And that His Majeſties ſaid Commiſſioner and other chief Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or Governours of this Kingdom for the time being, ſhall cauſe whatſoever ſhall be further directed by His Majeſty to be paſſed in Parliament, for and on the behalf of His ſaid Roman Catholique Subjects, to be accordingly drawn into Bills, and tranſmitted according to the uſual maner, to be afterwards paſſed as Acts in the ſaid Parliament.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded and agreed upon, by and between the ſaid parties, And His Majeſty is graciouſly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to call a new Parliament to be held in this Kingdom, on or before the laſt day of <hi>November</hi> next enſuing, and that all matters agreed on by theſe: Articles to be paſſed in Parliament, ſhall be tranſmitted into <hi>England,</hi> according the uſual form, to be paſſed in the ſaid Parliament, and that the ſaid Acts ſo to be agreed upon, and ſo to be paſſed, ſhall receive no alteration or diminution here or in <hi>England;</hi> Provided, that nothing ſhall be concluded by both or either of the ſaid Houſes of Parliament, which may bring prejudice to any of His Majeſties Proteſtant Party, or their Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, or to any of His Majeſties Roman Catholique Subjects party, or their Adherents, other then ſuch things as upon this Treaty ſhall be concluded to be done, or ſuch things as may be proper for the Committee of Priviledges of either or both Houſes, to take cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of, as in ſuch caſes heretofore hath been accuſtomed, and ſuch other things as ſhall be propounded to either or both Houſes by the Lord Lieutenant, or other chief Governour or Governour
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96244:6"/>for the time being, during the ſaid Parliament, for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of His Majeſties Service, and the Peace of the Kingdom, which Clauſe is to admit no conſtruction, which may trench upon theſe Articles or any of them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded and agreed upon, by and between the ſaid parties, And His Majeſty is further graciouſly pleaſed, that all Acts, Ordinances and Orders made by both or either Houſes of Parliament, to the blemiſh, diſhonor, or prejudice of His Majeſties Roman Catholique Subjects of this Kingdom, or any of them, ſithence the 7. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1641. ſhall be vacated, and that the ſame, and all exemplifications, and other Acts, which may continue the memory of them, be made void by Act of Parliament.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded and agreed upon, by and-between the ſaid parties, And His Majeſty is further graciouſly pleaſed, that all Indictments, Attainders, Outlawries in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and all the Proceſſes and other proceedings thereupon, and all Letters Patents, Grants, Leaſes, Cuſtodiams, Bonds, Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zances, and all Records, Act or Acts, Office or Offices, Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all other things depending upon, or taken by reaſon of the ſaid Indictments, Attainders, or Outlawries, ſithence the 7. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1641. in prejudice of the ſaid Catholiques, their Heirs, Executors, Adminiſtrators and Aſſigns, or any of them, or the Widows of them or any of them, ſhall be vacated and made void in ſuch ſort, as no memory ſhall remain thereof to the blemiſh, diſhonor, or prejudice of the ſaid Catholiques, their Heirs, Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, Adminiſtrators or Aſſigns, or any of them, or the Widows of them or any of them, and that to be done immediately after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding of theſe Articles, and at furtheſt before the firſt day of <hi>October</hi> next; Or in caſe the ſaid new Parliament be called ſooner then the ſaid laſt day of <hi>November,</hi> then fourty days before the ſaid Parliament. And that all impediments which may hinder the ſaid Roman Catholiques to Sit or Vote in the next intended Parliament, or to chooſe or to be choſen Knights and Burgeſſes to Sit or Vote there, ſhall be removed before the ſaid Parliament, Provided, that no man ſhall be queſtioned by reaſon of this Article for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96244:6"/>meſne rates or waſtes, ſaving wilful waſtes committed after the firſt of <hi>November,</hi> 1645.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded and agreed upon, by and between the ſaid parties, And His Majeſty is further graciouſly pleaſed, that all debts do ſtand in ſtate as they were in the beginning of thoſe troubles, and that no grant or diſpoſition made, or to be made, thereof, by vertue or colour of any Attainder, Outlawry, Fugacy or other Forfeiture whatſoever, or otherwiſe, ſhall be of force, and this to be paſſed as an Act in the ſaid next Parliament.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Item,</hi> It is concluded, accorded and agreed, by and between the ſaid parties, And His Majeſty is graciouſly pleaſed, that for the ſecuring of the Eſtates or reputed Eſtates, of the Lords, Knights, Gentlemen and Freeholders, or reputed Freeholders, as well of <hi>Connaught,</hi> and County of <hi>Clare,</hi> or Country of <hi>Thomond,</hi> as of the County of <hi>Limerick</hi> and <hi>Tipperary,</hi> the ſame to be ſecured by Act of Parliament according to the intent of the 25 Article of the Graces, granted in the fourth year of His Majeſties Reign, the Tenor whereof, for ſo much as concerneth the ſaid Propoſition, doth enſue in theſe words, viz. <hi>Wee are Graciouſly pleaſed, that for the ſecuring of the Inhabitants of</hi> Connaught, <hi>and Country of</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, <hi>and County of</hi> Clare, <hi>that their ſeveral Eſtates ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed unto them and their Heirs, againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, and our Heirs and Succeſſors, by Act to be paſſed in the next Parliament to be holden in</hi> Ireland, <hi>to the end the ſame may never hereafter be brought into any further queſtion by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, Our Heirs and Succeſſors; In which Act of Parliament ſo to be paſſed, you are to take care, that all Tenures</hi> in Capite, <hi>and all Rents and Services, as are now due, or which ought to be anſwered unto <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, out of the ſaid Lands and Premiſes by any Letters Patents paſt thereof, ſince the firſt year of King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eight, or found by any Office taken from the ſaid firſt year of King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eight, until the</hi> 21. <hi>of</hi> July, 1615. <hi>Whereby our late dear Father, or any His Predeceſſors actually received any profit, by Wardſhip, Liveries, primer Seiſins, meſne rates, Ouſter le mains, or fines of alienations without licence, be again reſerved unto <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, Our Heirs and Succeſſors; And all the reſt of the premiſes to be holden
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96244:7"/>of our Caſtle of</hi> Athloane, <hi>by Knights Service, according to Our ſaid late Fathers Letters, notwithſtanding any Tenures</hi> in Capite <hi>ſound for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s by Office ſince the</hi> 21. <hi>of</hi> July, 1615. <hi>And not appearing in any ſuch Letters Patents, or Offices,</hi> within which rule it is His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties pleaſure, and it is ſo concluded and agreed, that the ſaid Lands in the Countreys of <hi>Limerick</hi> and <hi>Tipperary,</hi> be included, but to be held by ſuch Rents and Tenures only as they were in the fourth year of His Majeſties Reign: Provided always, and it is the intention of the ſaid parties to theſe preſents, that the ſaid Lords, Knights, Gentlemen and Freeholders, or reputed Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders of the ſaid Province of <hi>Connaught,</hi> County of <hi>Clare,</hi> and Country of <hi>Thomond,</hi> and Counties of <hi>Tipperary</hi> and <hi>Limerick,</hi> ſhall have and enjoy the full benefit of ſuch Compoſition and Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which ſhall be made with His moſt Excellent Majeſty for the Court of Wards, Tenures, Reſpites and Iſſues of Homage, any clauſe in this Article contained to the contrary notwithſtanding: And as for the Lands within the Counties of <hi>Kilkenny</hi> and <hi>Wickloe,</hi> unto which His Majeſty was Intituled by Offices taken or found in the time of the Earl of <hi>Straffords</hi> Government is this Kingdom; His Majeſty is graciouſly pleaſed, that the ſtate thereof ſhall be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the next intended Parliament, wherein His Majeſty will aſſent unto that which ſhall be juſt and Honorable; And it is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concluded and agreed, by and between the ſaid parties, and His Majeſty is further graciouſly pleaſed, that the like Act of Limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of His Majeſties Titles for the ſecurity of the Eſtates of His Subjects of this Kingdom, be paſſed in the ſaid Parliament, as was Enacted in the 21. year of His late Majeſty King <hi>James</hi> His Reign in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded and agreed upon, by and between the ſaid parties, And His Majeſty is further graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly pleaſed, that all Incapacities, impoſed upon the Natives of this Kingdom, or any of them as Natives, by any Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Proviſoes in Patents, or otherwiſe, be taken away by Act to be paſſed in the ſaid Parliament; And that they may be enabled to erect one or more Inns of Court, in or neer the City of <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> and that ſuch Students, Natives of this Kingdom, as ſhall be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96244:7"/>therein, may take and receive the uſual Degrees accuſtomed in any Innes of Court, they taking the enſuing Oath, viz. <q>
                  <hi>I.</hi> A. B. <hi>do truly acknowledge, profeſſe and declare in my Conſcience, before God and the World, That our Soveraign Lord King</hi> Charles <hi>is Lawful and Rightful King of this Realm, and of other His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Dominions and Countreys, and I will bear Faith and true Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to His Majeſty, and His Heirs and Succeſſors, and Him and them will defend to the uttermoſt of my power, againſt all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies and Attempts whatſoever, which ſhall be made againſt His or their Crown and Dignity; and do my beſt endeavour to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe and make known to His Majeſty, His Heirs and Succeſſors, or to the Lord Deputy or Governors for the time being, all Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or Trayterous Conſpiracies which I ſhall know or hear to be intended againſt His Majeſty or any of them; and I do make this Recognition and Acknowledgement Heartily, and Willingly, and Truly, upon the true Faith of a Chriſtian: So help me</hi> GOD.</q> And that they may erect one or more Univerſities, to be Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſuch Rules and Orders as His Majeſty ſhall appoint: And it is further concluded and agreed, by and between the ſaid parties, and His Majeſty is graciouſly pleaſed, that the ſaid Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Subjects may erect and keep Free-Schools for education of Youth in this Kingdom, any Law or Statute to the contrary notwithſtanding; all the matters of this Article to be paſſed as Acts of Parliament in the ſaid next Parliament.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded and agreed upon, by and between the ſaid parties, and His Majeſty is graciouſly pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That places of Command, Honor, Profit and Truſt in His Majeſties Armies in this Kingdom, ſhall be upon perfection of theſe Articles actually, and by particular inſtances conferred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on His Roman Catholique Subjects of this Kingdom; And that upon the diſtribution, conferring and diſpoſal of the places of Command, Honor, Profit and Truſt in His Majeſties Armies in this Kingdom, for the future no differnnce ſhall be made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſaid Roman Catholiques, and other His Majeſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but that ſuch diſtribution ſhall be made with equal indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency, according to their reſpective Merits and Abilities; And
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96244:8"/>that all his Majeſties Subjects of this Kingdom, as well Roman Catholiques as others, ſhall for his Majeſties Service and their own ſecurity, arme themſelves the beſt they may, wherein they ſhall have all fitting encouragement, And that places of Command, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Profit and Truſt in Civil Government in this Kingdom, ſhall be, upon paſſing of the Bills, in theſe Articles mentioned, in the next Parliament, actually and by particular inſtances conferred upon His Majeſties Roman Catholique Subjects of this Kingdom, And that in the Diſtribution, conferring, and diſpoſal of the places of Command, Honor, Profit and Truſt, in the Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for the future, no difference ſhall be made between the ſaid Roman Catholiques and others His Majeſties Subjects, but that ſuch diſtribution ſhall be made with equal indifferency, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their reſpective Merits, and abilities, And that in the diſtribution of Miniſterial Offices, or Places which now are, or hereafter ſhall be, voyd in this Kingdom, equality ſhall be uſed to the Roman Catholique natives of this Kingdom as to other His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Subjects; That the Command of Forts, Caſtles Gariſons, Towns, and other Places of Importance in this Kingdom, ſhall be conferred upon His Majeſties Roman Catholique Subjects of this Kingdom upon perfection of theſe Articles, actually and by particular inſtances, and that in the diſtribution, conferring and diſpoſal of the Forts Caſtles, Gariſons Towns and other places of Importance in this Kingdom, no difference ſhall be made between His Majeſties Roman Catholique Subjects of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and other His Majeſties Subjects, but that ſuch diſtribution ſhall be made with equal indifferency, according to their reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive Merits and Abilities.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded and agreed upon, by and between the ſaid parties, and His Majeſty is further Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly pleaſed, That His Majeſty will accept of the yearly Rent or annual ſum of Twelve Thouſand pounds ſterlin, to be applotted with indifferency and equalily, and conſented to be paid to His Majeſty His Heires and Succeſſors in Parliament, for and in lieu of the Court of Wards in this Kingdom, <hi>Tenures in Capite, common Knights ſervice,</hi> and all other Tenures within the cognizance of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96244:8"/>that Court, And for and in lieu of all Wardſhips, primer Seiſms, Fines, Ouſterlemaines, Liveries, Intruſions, Alienations; Meſne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, Reliefes and all other Profits, within the cognizance of the ſaid Court, or incident to the ſaid Tenures or any of them, or Fines to accrew to His Majeſty, by reaſon of the ſaid Tenures or any of them, and for, and in lieu of Reſpites, and Iſſues of Homage, and Fines for the ſame; And the ſaid yearly rent being ſo Applotted and conſented unto in Parliament as aforeſaid, then a Bill is to be agreed on in the ſaid Parliament, to be paſſed as an Act, for the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the ſaid yearly Rent, or annual ſum of Twelve Thouſand pounds, to be applotted as aforeſaid, and for the Extinction and taking away of the ſaid Court, and other matters aforeſaid in this Article contained; And it is further agreed, that reaſonable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions ſhall be accepted for Wardſhips fallen ſince the 23. of <hi>October</hi> 1641. and already granted; And that no wardſhips fallen, and not granted, or that ſhall fall, ſhall be paſt, until the ſucceſſe of this Article ſhall appear; And if His Majeſty be Secured as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, Then all Wardſhips fallen ſince the ſaid 23. of <hi>October,</hi> are to be included in the agreement aforeſaid, upon Compoſition to be made with ſuch as have grants as aforeſaid, which compoſition to be made with the grantees ſince the time aforeſaid, it to be left to indifferent perſons, and the umpirage to the ſaid Lord Lieutenant His Majeſties Commiſſioner.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded and agreed, by and between the ſaid parties, and His Majeſty is further gratiouſly pleaſed, that no Nobleman or Peer of this Realm in Parliament ſhall be hereafter capable of more Proxies then two, and that blanck Proxies ſhall be hereafter totally diſallowed, and that if ſuch Noblemen or Peers of this Realm as have no Eſtates in this Kingdom do not within five years, to begin from the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of theſe Articles, Purchaſe in this Kingdom as followeth, <hi>viz. A Lord Baron two hundred pounds per annum, a Lord Viſcount four hundred pounds per annum, and an Earl ſix hundred pounds ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per annum,</hi> ſhall loſe their votes in Parliament until ſuch time as they ſhall afterwards acquire ſuch eſtates reſpectively; And it is further agreed, that none be admitted into the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons but ſuch as ſhall be Eſtated, and Reſident within this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96244:9"/>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded and agreed by and between the ſaid parties, and His Majeſty is further gratiouſly pleaſed, that as for and concerning the Independency of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>Ireland</hi> of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> His Majeſty will leave both Houſes of Parliament in this Kingdom to make ſuch Declaration therein as ſhall be agreeable to the Laws of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded and agreed, by and between the ſaid parties, and His Majeſty is further gratiouſly pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That the Councel Table ſhall contain it ſelf within it's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per bounds in handling matters of State and weight fit for that place, amongſt which, the Patents of Plantation, and the Offices whereupon thoſe Grants are founded, are to be handled as matters of State, and be Heard and Determined by the Lord Lieutenant or other chief Governor or Governors for the time being and the Councel, publiquely at the Councel board, and not otherwiſe; but Titles between party and party, grown after theſe Patents granted, are to be left to the ordinary courſe of Law; and that the Councel Table do not hereafter intermeddle with common buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that is within the cognizance of the ordinary Courts, nor with the altering of Poſſeſſions of Lands, nor make, nor uſe private Orders, Hearings, or References concerning any ſuch matter, nor grant any Injunction or Order for ſtay of any Suites in any Civil Cauſe, and that parties grieved, for or by reaſon of any proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings formerly had there, may commence their ſuits and proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the ſame, in any of His Majeſties Courts of Juſtice or Equity, for remedy of their pretended Rights, without any reſtraint or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption from His Majeſty, or otherwiſe by the chief Governor or Governors and Councel of this Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, granted and agreed, by and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſaid parties, and His Majeſty is further gratiouſly pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that as for and concerning one Statute made in this Kingdom in the eleventh yeer in the Raign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> intituled <hi>An Act for ſtaying of Wooll, Flocks, Tallow,</hi> and other neceſſaries within this Realm, and one other Statute made in the ſaid King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the 12 year of the ſaid Queen intituled <hi>An Act.</hi> 
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96244:9"/>
            <p>And one other Statute, made in the ſaid Kingdome in the 13. yeare of the raigne of the ſaid late Queene intituled, <hi>An explanation of the Act made in a Seſſion of this Parliament for the ſtaying of Wooll, Flockes, Tallow and other Wares and Commodities</hi> mentioned in the ſaid Act, and certaine Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles added to the ſame Act, All concerning Staple or Native com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of this Kingdome, ſhall be repealed, excepting for Wooll and Wooll fels, and that ſuch indifferent perſons, as ſhall be agreed on by the ſaid Lord Lievtenant, and the ſaid Lord viſc. <hi>Mountgarret, Donnogh Lord Viſcount Muskery, Sir Daniell ó Bryen Knight, Sir Lucas Dillon Knight, Nicholas Plunket, Richard Bellings, Philip mac Hugh Rely, Tirlogh ó Neale, Thomas Fleming, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricke Darcy, Gerrald Fernell &amp; Geffry Browne Eſquires</hi> or any five or more of them ſhall be Authorized by Commiſſion under the great Seale, to Moderate and Aſcertaine the Rates of Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize to be exported, or Imported, out of, or into, this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome as they ſhall thinke fit.</p>
            <p n="14">14. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded and agreed, by and betweene the ſaid parties, and his Majeſtie is further gratiouſly pleaſed, that care be had, that the chiefe Governor, or Governors, of this Kingdome for the time being, ſhall not continue in thoſe Places longer then he ſhall finde for the good of his people here, and that they ſhall be inhibited to make any Purchaſe other then by Leaſe for Proviſion of their Houſes, dureing the time of their Government.</p>
            <p n="15">15. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded accorded &amp; agreed, by &amp; between the ſaid parties, and his Majeſtie in further gratiouſly pleaſed, that an Act of oblivion ſhall be paſſed in the next Parliament to extend unto all his Majeſties Subjects, of this Kingdome and their adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, of all Treaſons &amp; Offences, Capitall, Criminall, and Perſonall, and other Offences of what Nature, kind, or qualitie ſoever, in ſuch manner, as if ſuch Treaſons or Offences had never beene com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted perpetrated or done, That the ſaid Act doe extend to the Heires, Children, Kindred, Executors, Adminiſtrators, Wifes, Widdowes, Dowagers, and Aſſignes, of ſuch of the ſaid Subjects,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96244:10"/>and their adherents, who died on, or ſince the 23 <hi>of October</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1. That the ſaid Act doe relate to the Firſt Day of the next Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; That the ſaid Act doe extend to all Bodies Politique, and Corporate, and their reſpective Succeſſors, and unto all Citties, Bourrougaes, Counties, Barronies, Hundreds, Townes, Villages, Tythings, and every of them within this Kingdome, for and concerning all and every of the ſaid offences, or any other offences or offences, in them or any of them committed or done, by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties ſaid Subjects or their adherents, or any of them, in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or ſince the 23. <hi>of October</hi> 1641. That this Act ſhall extend to Piracies and all other Offences, committed upon the Sea by his Majeſties ſaid Subjects, or their adherents, or any of them, That in this Act of Oblivion, words of Releaſe, Aquittall, and Diſcharge, be incerred; That no perſon or Perſons, Bodies Politique or Corporate, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Cities, Burroughes, Barronies, Hundreds, Townes, Villages, Tythings, or any of them within this Kingdome, included within the ſaid Act, be Troubled, Impeached, Sued, Inquieted, or Moleſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for, or by reaſon of any offence, matter or thing, whatſoever, comprized within the ſaid Act, and the ſaid Act ſhall extend to all Rents, Goods, and Chattells taken, Detained, or growen due, to the Subjects of the one ſide to the other, ſince the 23. <hi>of October</hi> 1641. to the Date of theſe Articks, and alſo to all Cuſtomes, Rents, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teares of Ren <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Prizes, Recognizances, Bonds, Fines, Forfeitures, Penalties and to all other Profits, perq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſites, and Dues, which were due, or did, or ſhould, accrue to his Majeſtie on, before or fince, the 23 of <hi>October</hi> 1641. untill the perfection of theſe Articles, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to all m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſue rates, Fines, of what nature ſoever, Recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizances, Iudgments, Executions thereupon, and penalties what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, and to all other profits due to his Majeſtie ſince the ſaid 23. <hi>of October</hi> and before untill this preſent, for, by, reaſon, or which lay within the ſurvay or cognizance of the Court of Wards; and alſo to all Reſpirts; Iſſues of Homage and Fines for the ſame, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided this ſhall not extend to Diſcharge or Remit any of the Kings Debts, or Subſidies, Due before the ſaid 23. <hi>of October</hi> 1641. which were then, or before, levyed, or taken by Sheriffs, Commiſſioners, Receivers, or Collectors, and not then, or before accounted for, or ſince diſpoſed to publique uſe of the ſaid Roman Catholique Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96244:10"/>but that ſuch perſons may be brought to account for the ſame, after full ſettlement in Parliament &amp; not before; Provided that ſuch Barbarous, and Inhumane Crimes, as ſhall be particularized, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon, by the ſaid Lord Lievtenant, and the Lord Viſcount <hi>Mountgarret, Doimogh</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Muskery,</hi> Sir <hi>Daniell ô Bryon</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Lucas Dillon</hi> Knight, <hi>Nicholas Plunket, Richard Bellings, Philip Mas Hugh Rely, Terlogh ô Neale, Thomas Flem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Patricks Darcy, Gerald Fennell</hi> and <hi>Goffry Brouns</hi> Eſquires, or any five or more of them, as to the Actors, and Procurers, thereof, be left to be Tried and Adjudged by ſuch indifferent Commiſſioners as ſhall be agreed upon by the ſaid Lord Lievtenant and the ſaid Lord viſcount <hi>Mountgarret, Donogh</hi> Lord viſc. <hi>Muskery,</hi> Sir <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niell ô Bryen</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Lucas Dillon</hi> Knight, <hi>Nicholas Planket, Richard Bellings, Philip mac hugh o Rely, Terlogh, o Neale Thomas Flewing, Patrick Darcy, Gerrald Fennell,</hi> and <hi>Geffry Browne</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, or any five or more of them, and that the power of the ſaid Commiſſioners ſhall continue only for two yeares next enſuing the date of theſe preſent Articles; Provided alſo that the Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſioners to be agreed on for tryall of the ſaid particular Crimes to be Excepted, ſhall Heare, Order &amp; Determine all caſes of Truſt, where releife may or ought in Equitie to be afforded againſt all manner of perſons according to the Equitie and Circumſtances of every ſuch eaſes; And his Majeſties Cheife Governor, or Governors, and other Governors and Majeſtrates for the time being, and all his Majeſties Courts of Iuſtice, and other his Majeſties Officers, of what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or quality ſoever, be bound and required to take notice of, and purſue the ſaid Act of Oblivion, without Pleading or Suite to be made for the ſame; And that no Clerke or other Officers doe make out, or write out, any manner of Writts, Proceſſes, Summons, or other Precept, for, concerning, or by reaſon of any matter, cauſe, or thing, whatſoever, Releaſed, Forgiven, Diſcharged, or to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given by the ſaid Act, under paine of twenty pound ſterling; And that no Sheriffe or other Officer doe execute any ſuch Writt, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, Summons, or Precept; And that no Record, Writeing, or Memorie, doe remaine of any Offence, or Offences, releaſed, or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, or mentioned to be Forgiven by this Act. And that all other cauſes uſually incerted in Acts of Generall Pardon or Oblivion, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96244:11"/>His Majeſties Grace, and Mercie, not herein particularied, be incerted and comprized, in the ſaid Act, when the Bill ſhall be drawn up, with the Exceptions already expreſſed, and none other; Provided alwaies that the ſaid Act of Oblivion, ſhall not extend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any Treaſon, Fellony or other Offence or Offences, which ſhall be Committed or done from or after the date of theſe Articles, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the firſt day of the before mentioned next Parliament to be held in this Kingdome; Provided alſo, that any Act or Acts which ſhall be done by vertue, pretence, or in perſuance, of theſe Articles or any of them, after the Publication of the ſaid Articles, or any Act or Acts which ſhall be done by vertue, colour, or pretence, of the power, or authoritie uſed, or exerciſed, by, &amp; amongſt, the confederat Roman Catholiques after the date of theſe Articles, and before the ſaid Publication ſhall not be accounted, taken, conſtrued, or be, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Fellony, or other offence, to be excepted out of the ſaid Act of oblivion, Provided likewiſe that the ſaid Act of oblivion ſhall not extend unto any perſon, or perſons, that will not Obey and Submit unto the Peace, Concluded, and agreed on, by theſe Articles.</p>
            <p n="16">16. <hi>Item.</hi> It is further concluded accorded &amp; agreed, by &amp; between the ſaid parties, and his Majeſty is further gratiouſly pleaſed, that an Act be paſſed in the next Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prohibiting that neither the Lord Deputy, or other chiefe Governor, Governors, Lord Chancellor; <hi>Lo.</hi> high Treaſurer vice treaſurer, Chancellor, or any of the Barrons of the Exch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quer Privie Councell, or Iudges of the foure Courts, be Farmours of His Majeſties Cuſtomes within this Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="17">17. <hi>Item.</hi> It is further concluded accorded and agreed, by and betweene the ſaid parties. And His Majeſtie is further graciouſly pleaſed, that an Act of Parliament paſſe in this Kingdome againſt Monoples, ſuch as was enacted in <hi>England</hi> 21. <hi>Iacobr Regis,</hi> with a further clauſe of Repealing of all grants of Monopoles in this Kingdome, and that Commiſſioners be agreed upon by the ſaid Lord Lievtenant, and the ſaid Lord Viſcount <hi>Mountgarret, Donogh</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Muskery,</hi> Sir <hi>Daniell ô Bryon</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Lucas Dillon</hi> Knight, <hi>Nicholas Plunket, Richard Bellings, Philip mac Hugh Rely, Terlogh ô Neale, Thomas Fleming, Patricke Darcy, Gerrald Fennell,</hi> and <hi>Geffry Browne</hi> Eſquires, or any five or more
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96244:11"/>of them, to ſet downe the Rates for the Cuſtome, or Impoſition to be laid on Aquavite, Wine, Oyle, Yarne, and Tobacco.</p>
            <p n="18">18. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded, and agreed, by and betweene the ſaid parties, and his Majeſtie is further graciouſly pleaſed, that ſuch perſons as ſhall be agreed on by the ſaid Lord Lievtenant, and the ſaid Lord Viſcount <hi>Mountgarret, Donogh</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Muskery,</hi> Sir <hi>Daniel ô Bryen,</hi> Knight; Sir <hi>Lucas Dillon,</hi> Knight; <hi>Nicholas Plunket, Richard Bellings, Philip mac Hugh Rely, Terlogh ô Neale, Thomas Fleming, Patricke Darcy. Gerrard Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, and Geffry Browne,</hi> Eſquires; or any five or more of them ſhall be upon concluſion of theſe Articles, Authorized by Commiſſion under the great Scale, to Regulate the Court of Caſtle Chamber, and ſuch cauſes as ſhall be brought into, and cenſured in, the ſaid Court.</p>
            <p n="19">19. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded and agreed, by and between the ſaid parties, And his Majeſtie is further graciouſly pleaſed, that two Acts lately paſſed in this Kingdome, prohibiting <hi>the Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ming with Horſes by the tayle, and the other prohibiting the burning of Oates in the Straw,</hi> be repealed.</p>
            <p n="20">20. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded, and agreed, by and betweene the ſaid parties, and His Majeſtie is further graciouſly pleaſed, that upon perfection of theſe Articles ſuch courſe ſhall be taken againſt ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> have Diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ayed the Ceſſation, and will not ſubmit to the Peace, if any ſhall Oppoſe it, as ſhall be juſt, and for the Peace of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="21">21. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded, and agreed, by and betweene the ſaid parties, And His Majeſtie is further graciouſly pleaſed, foraſmuch as upon application of Agents from this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome unto His Majeſtie in the fourth yeare of his Raigne, and late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon humble Suite made unto His Majeſtie by a Committee of both Houſes of the Parliament of this Kingdome, Order was given by his Majeſtie for Redreſſe of ſeverall grievances, and for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe as are not expreſſed in theſe Articles, whereof both Houſes in the next enſuing Parliament ſhall deſire the benefit of His Majeſties ſaid former directions for Redreſſes therein, that the ſame be afforded them, yet ſo, as for prevention of inconveniences to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96244:12"/>His Majeſties ſervice, that the warning mentioned the 21. Article of the graces, in the fourth yeare of his Majeſties Raign, be ſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that the Warning being left at the perſons dwelling houſes, be held ſufficient Warning, and that, as to the 22 Article of the ſaid Graces, the Proceſſe hitherto uſed in the Court of Wards doe ſtill contin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e as hitherto it hath done in that, and hath been uſed in other Engliſh Courts, but the Court of Wards being compounded for, ſo much of the aforeſaid Anſwer as concernes Warning, and Proceſſe, ſhall be omitted.</p>
            <p n="22">22. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further Concluded, Accorded, and Agreed, by and betweene the ſaid parties, and His Majeſtie is further graciouſly pleaſed, that Maratine cauſes may be determined in this Kingdom, without driving of marchants or others to Appeale, and ſeek Juſtice elſewhere; and if it ſhall fall out that there be cauſe of an Appeale, the party grieved is to appeale to His Majeſtie in the Chancerie of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Sentence thereupon to be given by the Delegaces, to be Definitive, and not to be queſtioned upon any further Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale, except it be in the Parliament of this Kingdome, if the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſhall then be ſitting, otherwiſe not, This to be by Act of Parliament.</p>
            <p n="23">23. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded, and agreed, by and between the ſaid parties. And His Majeſty out of His abundant grace and goodneſſe to His Subjects of this Kingdome is graciouſly pleaſed to aſſent, that His ſaid Subjects be eaſed of the increaſe of Rents lately raiſed on them upon the Commiſſion of Defective Titles, in the Earle of <hi>Straffords</hi> Government, this to be by Act of Parliament.</p>
            <p n="24">24. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded, and agreed upon, by and between the ſaid parties, And His Majeſtie is further graciouſly pleaſed, that by Act to be paſſed in the next Parliament, all the arreares of Intereſt of money which did accrew, or grow due by way of debt, mortgage, or otherwiſe, and yet not ſatisfied, ſince the 23. of <hi>October,</hi> 1641. Untill the perfection of theſe Articles ſhall be fully forgiven and be releaſed; And that for and during the ſpace of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96244:12"/>three yeares next enſuing, no more ſhall be taken for uſe, or intereſt of money, then five pounds <hi>per Cont.</hi> and in all caſes of equity ariſing through diſability occaſioned by the diſtempers of thoſe times, the conſiderations of equitie to be alike unto both parties.</p>
            <p n="25">25. <hi>Item,</hi> It is concluded, accorded, and agreed, by and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſaid parties, And His Majeſtie is graciouſly pleaſed that the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Mountgarret, Donogh</hi> Lord Viſc-<hi>Muskery,</hi> Sir <hi>Daniel ô Bryen,</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Lucas Dillon,</hi> Knight 3 <hi>Nicholas Pluncket, Richard Bellings, Phillip mac Hugh ô Redy, Terlogh ô Neale, Thomas Fleminge, Patricks Darcy, Gerrald Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell,</hi> and <hi>Goffrey Browne,</hi> Eſquires, ſhall be imediatly upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of theſe Articles, Authorized by Act of State to proceed in, Heare, Determine, &amp; Execute within the Cities, corporate Towns, Counties and part of Counties, now, or late, within the Quarters of the ſaid Confederate Catholiques, the enſuing particulars, and all matters thereupon depending, And that the ſaid Act of State, and other the authorities hereafter mentioned ſhall remaine of force without Revoration, Alteration, or Diminution, untill Acts of Parliament be Paſſed according the purport and intent of theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Articles; onely in caſe of death of any of the ſaid perſons ſo to be authorized, the Lord Lievtenant, or other chiefe Governour or Governors of this Kingdome for time being, ſhall by the advice and conſent of the perſons ſo to be authorized, then living, or any five or more of them, name others in the place of ſuch who ſhall be ſo dead, and the perſons ſo to be named, to be Authorized as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, And that the perſons to be Authorized as aforeſaid, or any five or more of them be permitted without interruption to Applot Raiſe and Levic Meanes with indifferencie and equallitie, upon all His Majeſties Roman Catholique Subjects of this Kingdome, for the Raiſing, Clothing, and bringing to Sea Ports, and Maintaining there, untill they be ſhipped Ten Thouſand men promiſed by the Conſederate Catholiques of this Kingdome to aſſiſt His Majeſty, and to levy the Arrearea of all Exciſes, and other Publique Taxes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready impoſed by them, and yet unpaid; and to call all Receivers and other Accomptants of all former taxes and publique dues, to a Juſt and ſtrict Accompt, either by themſelves, or by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96244:13"/>ſuch as they, or any five or more of them ſhall name and appoint, And that the ſaid perſons to be authorized as aforeſaid, or any five or more of them ſhall have power to Applot, Raiſe, and Levie, meanes, with indifferencie and equality, by way of Exciſes, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, in the ſeverall Cities, Corporate Townes, Counties and parts of Counties now within the Quarters of the ſaid Confederate Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques, towards the Maintenance of ſuch Army or Armies as ſhall be thought fit to continue, and be in pay, for the defence of the Kingdome, and towards the maintenance of all the Forts, Caſtles, and Garriſons within both, or either, of the now Quarters of either partie, other then ſuch of the ſaid Garriſons, Forts, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, as from time to time, untill there be a ſettlement in Parliament, ſhall be thought fit by His Majeſties chiefe Governour, or Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of this Kingdome for the time being, by and with the adviſe and conſent of the ſaid perſons ſo to be authorized, or any five or more of them, not to be maintained at the Charge of the Publique, Provided that His Majeſties Lievtenant, or other chiefe Governors for the time being, be firſt made acquainted with ſuch Taxes, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies, and Exciſes as ſhall be made, and the manner of Levying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and that he approve the ſame, And that the perſons to be autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized as aforeſaid, or any five or more of them ſhall be authorized to appoint Receivers, Gollectors, and all other Officers, for ſuch mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies as ſhall be ſo aſſeſſed, and for the Arreares of all former Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plotments, Taxes, and other Publique Dues yet unpaid, And that the perſons ſo to be authorized, or any five or more of them, in caſe of Refractorineſſ', or Delinquencie, may Diſtraint, and Impriſon, and cauſe ſuch Delinquents to be Diſtrained or Impriſoned, and that the Profits of the Eſtates, within the now Quarters of the Confederate Catholiques, of ſuch as ſhall adhere to the Parliament, and not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Peace, be accompted as Publique Dues, and be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Maintenance of the Kings Armie, And that the ſaid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be authorized as aforeſaid, or any five or more of them, ſhall have power to Applot, Raiſe, and Levy meanes with indifferencie, and equalitie, for the buying of Armes and Ammunition, and for Entertaining of Friggors, in ſuch proportion and manner as ſhall be thought fit by His Majeſties Lievtenant, or other chiefe Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, or Governors, for the time being, by and wish the Advice and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96244:13"/>conſent of the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord viſcount <hi>Mountgarret, Donnogh</hi> Lord viſcount <hi>Muskery,</hi> Sir <hi>Daniell ô Bryen</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Lucas Dillon</hi> Knight, <hi>Nicholas Plunket, Richard Bellings, Philip mac Hugh ô Rely, Terlogh ô Neale, Thomas Fleming, Patricke Darcy, Gerrard Fennell</hi> and <hi>Geffry Browne</hi> Eſquires, or any five or more of them, The ſaid Armes and Ammunition, to be laid up in ſuch Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazines, and under the charge of ſuch perſons as ſhall be agreed, by the ſaid Lord Lievtenant, and the ſaid perſons to be authorized, as aforeſaid, or any five or more of them, and to be iſſued, and the ſaid Frigotts to be employed, by the Lord Lievtenant or other cheife Governor, or Governors for the time being, for the ſafety of the Kingdome, by the advice and conſent of the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>Mountgarret, Donnogh</hi> Lord viſcount <hi>Muskery,</hi> Sir <hi>Daniell ô Bryen,</hi> Sir <hi>Lucas Dillon, Nicholas Plunket, Richard Bellings, Philip mac Hugh ô Rely, Terlogh ô Neale, Thomas Fleming, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricke Darcy, Gerrald Fennell, and Geffry Browne,</hi> or any five or more of them; And that the ſaid perſons ſo to be authorized as aforeſaid, or any five or more of them ſhall have power to Applot, Raiſe, and Levie, Mesnes with indifferencie, and equality, by way of Exciſes, or otherwiſe, in the ſeverall Citties Corporate Townes, Counties and parts of Counties, now within the Quarters and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Eſtates of the ſaid Confederate Catholiques all ſuch ſumme and ſummes as ſhall appeare unto the ſaid perſons, to be authorized as aforeſaid, or any five or more of them, to be really due, for, and in diſcharge of, the publique ingagements of the ſaid Confederate Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques incurred or growen due before the Concluſion of theſe Articles, and that the ſaid perſons to be authorized as aforeſaid, or any five or more of them ſhall have power to Applor, Raiſe, and Levie Meanes with indifferencie and equality by way of Exciſe, or otherwiſe, in the ſeverall Cities, Corporate Townes; Counties and parts of Counties now within the Quarters of the ſaid Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Catholiques as well for the perſons to be authorized as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and alſo for ſuch other perſon and perſons as ſhall be Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Publique Affaires within the ſeverall Citties, Corporate townes, Counties, and parts of Counties within the now Quarters of the ſaid Confederate Catholiques from time to time untill a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement by Parliament, And that the ſaid perſons to be Authorized
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96244:14"/>as aforeſaid, or any five or more of them, make perfect Bookes of all ſuch monies as ſhall be Applotted, Raiſed, and Levied, our of which Books, they are to make ſeverall and reſpective Abſtracte, to be delivered under their hands, or the hands of any five or more of them, to the ſeverall and reſpective Collectors, who ſhall be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to Levie, &amp; Receive the ſame; and that a duplicate of the ſaid Bookes, under the hands of the ſaid perſons to be authorized as aforeſaid, be delivered unto His Majeſties Lievtenant, or other Chiefe Governor or Governors for the time being, whereby a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect accompt might be given.</p>
            <p n="26">26. <hi>Item.</hi> It is further concluded, accorded, and agreed, by and between the ſaid parties and His Majeſty is gratiouſly pleaſed, that for the preſervation of the Peace, &amp; Tranquillity of the Kingdome, That the ſaid Lord Lievtenant, and the ſaid Lord viſcount <hi>Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garret, Donnogh</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Muskery,</hi> Sir <hi>Daniell ô Bryen</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Lucas Dillon</hi> Knight, <hi>Nicholas Plunket, Richard Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings Philip mac Hugh ô Rely, Terlogy ô Neale, Thomas Fleming, Patricke Darcy, Gerrald Fennell, and Geffry Browne</hi> Eſquires, or any five or more of them, ſhall for the preſent, agree upon ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who are to be authorized by Commiſſion under the great Seal, to be Commiſſioners of the Peace, <hi>Oyer and Terminer,</hi> and Goale delivery, in the ſeverall Counties, and parts of Counties, within the now Quarters of the Confederate Catholikes, with ſuch pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er as Iuſtices of the Peace, <hi>Oyerand Terminer,</hi> and Gaole delivery, in former times of Peace, have uſuall had; which is not to extend unto any Crime, or Offence, committed before the 15. of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 1643. And to be qualiffied with Power to Heare and Determine all Civill cauſes coming before them not exceeding ten pounds; Provided that they ſhall not intermedle with Titles of Lands; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided likewiſe the authoritie of ſuch Commiſſioners ſhall not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, to queſtion any perſon or perſons, for any Cattle or Goods, heretofore taken by either party from the other, contrary to the Articles of ceſſations, but that the ſame ſhall be left to be determined in ſuch way, as by theſe Articles is already preſcribed, which Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners are to continue till ſettlement by Parliament, <hi>Si tam diu ſe bene geſſerint,</hi> And if any who ſhall be ſo intruſted, ſhall misbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96244:14"/>himſelfe in the execution of ſuch truſt, within that time, that then ſuch other perſon or perſons ſhall be appointed in his or their place, as ſhall be agreed on by His Majeſties Chiefe Governour, or Governours for the time being, by the Advice and Conſent of the ſaid perſons ſo to be intruſted, or any five or more of them, and the ſaid Commiſſioners are to make their Eſtreates as accuſtomed in time of Peace, and ſhall take the enſuing Oath, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>You ſhall ſweare that as Juſtice of the Peace, Oyer and Terminer, and Goale delivery, in the Counties of A. B. C. in all Articles of the Kings Commiſſion to you directed, you ſhall doe equall right to the poore and to the rich, after your Cunning Wit, and Power, and after the Lawes &amp; Cuſtomes of the Realme, and in perſuance of theſe Articles; and you ſhall not be of Councell of any quarrel hanging before you, And the Iſſues, Eines, and Amerciaments, which ſhall happen to be made, and all Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which ſhall happen before you; You ſhall cauſe to be entr d with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any concealement or imbezeling, and truly ſend to the Kings Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer; You ſhall not lett for gift, or other cauſe, but well and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you ſhall doe your Office of juſtice of the Peace, Oyer and Termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and Gaole deliverie in that behalfe, and that you take nothing for your Office of Juſtice of the Peace, Oyer and Terminer and Gaole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery to be done, but of the King, and Fees accuſtomed; And you ſhall not direct, or cauſe to be directed, any warrant by you to be made to the parties, but you ſhall direct them to the Sheriffs, and Bayliffs of the ſaid Counties reſpectively, or other the Kings Officers, or Miniſters, or other indifferent perſons to doe Execution thereof, So helpe you God.</q> And that as well in the ſaid Commiſſion, as in all other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions and authorities, to be iſſued in perſuance of theſe preſent Articles, this Clauſe ſhall be incerted, <hi>viz.</hi> That all Officers, Civill and Marſhall, ſhall be required to be ayding and aſſiſting, and obedient unto the ſaid Commiſſioners, and other perſons to be autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized as aboveſaid in the execution of their reſpective powers.</p>
            <p n="27">27. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further Concluded, accorded, and agreed, by and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſaid Parties, And his Majeſty is further graciouſly pleaſed, That none of the now Roman Catholique party ſhall from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, untill there be a ſettlement by Parliament, Sue, Impleade, or Arreſt, or be ſued, Impleaded, or Arreſted in any Court, Place. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96244:15"/>or Tribunall, or before any Judge, Juſtice, or Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner whatſoever, other then before the Commiſſioners aforeſaid, or in the ſeverall Corporations, or other Judicatures, within the now Quarters of the ſaid Confederate Catholiques, as hath, or have Power derived from His Majeſtie.</p>
            <p n="28">28. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded, and agreed, by and betweene the ſaid parties, and His Majeſtie is further graciouſly pleaſed, that His Majeſties Confederate Catholique Subjects doe continue the poſſeſſion, of ſuch of His Majeſties Cities, Garriſons, Townes, Forts, and Caſtles, which are within their now Quarters, untill ſettlement by Parliament, and to be Commanded, Ruled and Governed in chiefe, by ſuch as His Majeſtie or his chiefe Governor of Governors of this Kingdome for the time being ſhall Appoint, and His Majeſtie his chiefe Governor or Governors of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome as aforeſaid, is to iſſue Commiſſions, and appoint ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and perſons, as ſhall be named by His Majeſties chiefe Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or Governours for the time being, by, and with the advice and conſent of the ſaid Lord Viſcount <hi>Mountgarret, Donnough,</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Muskery,</hi> Sir <hi>Daniel ô Bryen,</hi> Sir <hi>Lucas Dillon, Nicholas Plunket, Richard Bellings, Philip mac Hugh ô Rely, Terlogh ô Neale, Thomas Fleming, Patricke Darcy, Gerrald Fennell, and Geffry Browne,</hi> Eſquires, or any five or more of them, for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of ſuch Command, Rule, or Government, to continue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till all the particulars in theſe preſent Articles agreed on to paſſe in Parliament, ſhall be accordingly paſſed; only in caſe of death, or Misbehaviour ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch other perſon or perſons to be appointed for the ſaid Command, Rule, and Government to be named and appointed in the Place, or places, of him, or them, who ſhall ſo die or Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>behave themſelves, as the Chiefe Governour or Governours, for the time being, by the advice and conſent of the ſaid Lord Viſcount <hi>Mountgarret,</hi> and the reſt of the above mentioned parties to be au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized as aforeſaid, or any five or more of them, ſhall thinke fit, and to be continued untill ſettlement in Parliament, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="29">29. <hi>Item,</hi> It is further concluded, accorded, and agreed, by and betweene the ſaid parties, and His Majeſtie is further graciouſly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96244:15"/>pleaſed, that all Cuſtomes belonging to His Majeſtie which from the perfection of theſe preſent Articles ſhall fall due within this Kingdome, ſhall be payed into his Majeſties Receipt, and to His uſe, any Requeſt, Clauſe, or Demand, in the Act of Oblivion, or in any other former Propoſitions to the contrary notwithſtanding; Provided, that all and every perſon and perſons, who are at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Intruſted within the now Quarters of the Confederate Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques, by them the ſaid Confederate Catholiques in the Entries, Receipts, Collections, or otherwiſe concerning the ſaid Cuſtomes, doe continue their reſpective Imployments in the ſame, untill full ſettlement in Parliament; other then as to ſuch, and ſo many of them, as to the chiefe Governour, or Governours, for the time being, by the advice and conſent of the ſaid Lord Viſcount <hi>Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garret,</hi> and the other perſons to be authorized as aforeſaid, or any five or more of them ſhall be thought fit to be altered, and then, and in ſuch caſe, or in caſe of death, or misbehaviour, or other alteration, of any ſuch perſon or perſons, ſuch other perſon or perſons to bee imployed as ſhall be thought fit, by the Chiefe Governour or Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours for the time being, by, and with the advice and Conſent of the ſaid Lord Viſcount <hi>Mountgarret,</hi> and the reſt of the perſons to be authorized as aforeſaid, or any five or more of them; And as to His Majeſties Rents to grow due, at Eaſter next, and from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, the ſame to be payable unto His Majeſtie notwithſtanding any thing contained in the Article of the Act of oblivion, or in any other Article to the contrary, but the ſame not to be Written for, or Levied, unitll a full ſettlement in Parliament, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="30">30. <hi>Item.</hi> It is further concluded, accorded, and agreed, by and betweene the ſaid parties; And His Majeſty is further graciouſly pleaſed, That the Commiſſioners of Oyer and Terminer, and Gaole delivery, to be named as aforeſaid, ſhall have Power to heare and Determine all Murthers, Manſlaughters, Rapes, Stealths, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Houſes, and Corne in Reeke, or Stacks, Robberies, Burgla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, force<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble entries, Detainers of Poſſeſſions, and other Offences, commiteed, or done, and to be committed and done from the 15 day of <hi>September,</hi> 1643. untill the firſt day of the next Parliament. Theſe preſent Articles, or any therein contained to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; Provided that the Authoritie of the ſaid Commiſſioners
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96244:16"/>ſhall not extend to queſtion any perſon, or perſons, for doing or Committing and Act whatſoever before the concluſion of this Treaty by vertue or colour of any Warrantor direction from thoſe in publique Authority among the Confederate Catholiques; nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any Act which ſhall be done after the perfecting and concluding of theſe Articles by vertue of pretence of any authoritie, which is now by theſe Articles agreed on; Provided alſo the ſaid Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhall not continue longer then to the firſt day of the next Parliament. In witneſſe whereof his Excellencie the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond,</hi> Lord Lievtenant of <hi>Jreland</hi> His Majeſties Commiſſioner to that part of theſe Articles remaining with the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Mountgarret, Donnogh,</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Muskery,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Talbot,</hi> Baronet; <hi>Dermot ô Bryen, Patrick Darcie, Geffry Browne,</hi> and <hi>John Dillon,</hi> Eſquires; And the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>Mountgarret, Donnogh,</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Muskery,</hi> Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat Talbot,</hi> Barronet; <hi>Dermot ô Bryen, Patricke Darcy, Geffry Browne and John Dillon,</hi> Eſquires; to that part of theſe Articles remaining with the ſaid Lord Lievtenant, have put their hands and ſeales at <hi>Dublin</hi> this 28 day of <hi>March</hi> 1646. and in the two and Twentieth yeare of the Raigne of our Soveraigne King CHARLES King of Great <hi>Brittaine, France and Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:96244:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
